<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An overture for founding &amp; maintaining of bibliothecks in every paroch throughout this kingdom: humbly offered to the consideration of this present assembly</title>
            <author>Kirkwood, James, 1650?-1709.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87794</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K648</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R227356</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895671</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895671</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153245</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87794)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153245)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2355:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An overture for founding &amp; maintaining of bibliothecks in every paroch throughout this kingdom: humbly offered to the consideration of this present assembly</title>
                  <author>Kirkwood, James, 1650?-1709.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed in the year,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By James Kirkwood. - Wing (CD-ROM edition).</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing (CD-ROM edition).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church libraries --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153245:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153245:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153245:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153245:2"/>
            <p>OVERTURE OR Founding &amp; Maintaining of BIBLIOTHECKS In every Paroch through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this KINGDOM: <hi>Humbly Offered to the Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of this preſent</hi> Aſſembly.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1699.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:153245:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:153245:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:153245:4"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:153245:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>An</hi> Overture <hi>for Establiſhing of</hi> Bibliothecks <hi>in every Paroch throughout this Kingdom.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT is as eſſential to the nature of Mankind to be deſirous of Knowledge, as it is for them to be rational Creatures, for we ſee no other end or uſe for our Reaſon, but to ſeek out and ſearch for the Knowledge of all theſe things of which we are Ignorant. For <hi>this ſore travel hath God given to the ſons of men, to be exerciſed therewith.</hi> That being born Naked, Indigent and Ignorant, we ſhould be forced to enquire by the help of Reaſon, into the Nature and Knowledge of all theſe things which are about us, and to Invent and Perfect all ſuch Arts and Manufactories, as are neceſſary for the ſupport of our Lives. All which things are ſo numerous, and the ways of attaining to the Knowledge of them ſo difficult, longſome and uncertain that it would be but a very ſmall Degree<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> even of the meaneſt Art or Science, which any man could attain unto by his own particular Study and Obſervation, if he were deſtitute of all theſe Helps we receive from others, by Word and Writing.</p>
            <p>Therefore to facilitat this ſore Travel, God hath endued Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind with a Faculty of Speech, whereby they may Teach and Communicat to one another, all ſuch Knowledges and Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as ſhall be found out by any one of them; that ſo every one ſtudying a part, and contributing the ſmall Mite of his Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations into the publick Stock, they might at length advance Knowledge and Learning to that Degree, which Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:153245:5"/>in this lapſed Eſtate is capable of. And that there might be ſome conſiderable Progreſs made in this Work at firſt; God did beſtow upon the firſt Men long Lives, with vigorous Imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and ſolid Judgments, that thereby they might both Acquire great Stocks of Knowledge and Obſervations, and might convoy them, or communicat them to many Degrees of their Poſterity.</p>
            <p>But Men abuſing this Bleſſing of long Life, and exerciſing their Thoughts only upon Evil and that continually: God in his Juſtice, was provoked to ſhorten their Lives, and to confound their Languages, whereby this way of conveying Knowledge by Word of Mouth, and Tradition became very imperfect, and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to many Inconveniencies: and therefore that theſe Means of encreaſing Knowledge, and of ſearching out all the Works of God might be ſtill continued amongſt Men; God in his Infinite Mercy, was graciouſly pleaſed to teach Men a new Way of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating their Thoughts and Words, by Writing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which he did when he did write the Law with his own Finger, upon the two Tables of Stone in Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> that thereby Men might more eaſily and univerſally communicat their Obſervations to all the reſt of Mankind, and might more certainly preſerve them to all Poſterity.</p>
            <p>By this Art of Writing, Knowledge and Learning were very much advanced; till Books became ſo numerous, and the way of writing with a Pen being both dear and ſlow, Students could acquire only a ſmall number of them, whereby many Books were neglected and loſt, and Learning came to a ſtand, and then at length fell into a great Decay, for Men turned their Wits and Studies, rather to collect and underſtand the Writings and Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of the Ancients, than to enquire into the Nature of the things themſelves, in ſo much that all Philoſophy was turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Opinions of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and <hi>Plato;</hi> and all Theology was lodged in the Opinion of the Church, or in the Popes Infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. Yea, Ignorance prevailed to that Degree, that it was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged and preached up, as the Mother of Devotion. But at
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:153245:5"/>length Printing, which is a more eaſy, ſpeedy and cheap way than Writing, was Invented; which remedied all theſe Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies of Writing, and ſo recovered Learning at its laſt Gaſp, out of its long continued and almoſt fatal Decay. Since which time, Learning hath taken-on as it were a new growth; and though it be not as yet recovered in ſeveral Parts, yet many Arts and Sciences are advanced to a far greater Degree, than what they had attained unto amongſt the Ancients. From all which Courſe of Providence, we may clearly perceive, that it is the Will and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of our Lord and Maker, that by ſore Travel, we ſhould ſearch out and know all his wonderful Works, that we may Admire and Adore his Infinite Wiſdom, Goodneſs, and other Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in them. As alſo, we may perceive that a full and univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal communicating of our Thoughts and Obſervations to one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, is the neceſſary and ordinary Means appointed by God, whereby we may Attain unto this natural Knowledge; ſo that whatſoever Inconveniencies do obſtruct this free and univerſal communicating our Thoughts and Inſtructions to one another, or do hinder Students from Attaining the Knowledge of all that hath been Diſcovered before them, muſt of neceſſity much retard the Advancement of Learning, and hinder the Encreaſe of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge amongſt us; and therefore do deſerve our ſerious Thoughts, and utmoſt Endeavours to remove them. Some of theſe Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies are, 1. Books are ſo vaſtly multiplied, and do ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe dayly, that moſt part of Students either want Money to buy any moderat Collection of them; or <hi>2ly,</hi> they want Conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience to keep them, for Books are very troubleſome to Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port from place to place, or <hi>3ly,</hi> they have them not in due time, while they are young and free from Cares; for after a Man is ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled in the World, then the Cares of his Family, and the Affairs of his Calling, do ſo take up his Mind, that he can have no time nor heart to ſtudy. 4. The Money that is beſtowed upon Books muſt be looked upon as loſt; and this certainly is a great Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement. 5. Many Books which a Student ſhall happen to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153245:6"/>buy, will after peruſal, be found little worth, at leaſt for his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, whereby he is lamentably diſappointed, and loſeth both his Money and time. 6. We live at much diſtance from theſe famous Towns where moſt part of Books are Printed, that there are many uſeful new Books Printed which we never hear of, and theſe we hear of, cannot be brought home to us without great Expenſes and Trouble. 7. Although a Student had all the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages that can be reaſonably expected in one man, yet he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not Acquire all the Books in the World, that may relate to the Subject he ſtudies; and ſo he will ſtill be uneaſie and ſuſpicious, that there may be ſomething worth his Knowledge in theſe Books he wants. And it is not to be expected, that any man can ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance or improve any Art or Science to a full Degree, till firſt he have a full and comprehenſive Knowledge of all that hath been written and diſcovered of that Subject before him: and thereforé compleat and free Libraries are abſolutely neceſſary for the Improving of Arts and Sciences, and for Advancing of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing amongſt us.</p>
            <p>For effectuating of this, and for remeding all the fore-named inconveniencies, it is modeſtly conceived with ſubmiſſion to bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Judgments, that the Founding and Maintaining of Biblio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecks in every Paroch within this Kingdom, will be a moſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual means, for thereby a Student will have compleat Libraries within a few Miles of the place where he ſhall happen to reſide, out of which he may eaſily furniſh himſelf from time to time, of all ſorts of Books fit for his purpoſe without Money, and that in his youth, while he hath health and ſtrength to Study, and is free from the cares of the World, neither can he be troubled with uſeleſs Books, ſeing he may preſently return them to the Biblio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theck and take others; and Laſtly, Theſe Libraries in a few years, will be full and compleat, being furniſhed, not only with all the valuable and uſefull Old Books in any Art or Science, but alſo with all the valuable New Books, ſo ſoon as ever they are heard of or ſeen in the World, as will clearly be demonſtrat afterwards.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:153245:6"/>
            <p>The Method and particulars which I think neceſſary for this Founding and Maintaining of Bibliothecks in every Paroch throughout this Kingdom, are theſe.</p>
            <p>1ſt. A convenient place in every Paroch muſt be ſet a part, and ſitted for keeping of Books.</p>
            <p>2ly. Every preſent Miniſter muſt give in all his Books, to the Bibliotheck of his own Paroch, at the ſight of the Heretors of the Paroch, who ſhall cauſe rank them conform to their volumns, and ſhall cauſe take exact Alphabetical Catalogues of them, with the place where, and the time when they are Printed, of which Catalogues, there muſt be four principal Coppies ſubſcribed by the Miniſter and Heretors of each Paroch; whereof one Copy ſhal be kept by the Miniſter, as an obligation upon the Paroch till he be payed for his Books, another ſhall be kept by the Heretors in a litle Chiſt in the Bibliotheck, that it may be an obligation upon the Keeper of the Bibliotheck, to be anſwerable for all theſe Books; the third muſt be kept in the Bibliotheck openly, that any Heretor of the Paroch, or Miniſter of the Presbyterie may get a double of it when they pleaſe; and the fourth Copy ſhall be ſent to the principal Library at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> to kept there for ſeveral uſes.</p>
            <p>3dly. For avoiding all debates and difficulties, that may ariſe between Heretors and Miniſters in valuing theſe Books, it will be fit that ſome Miniſters and Heretors be appointed to draw out a general Catalogue of all the Books in the Kingdom, out of thoſe particular Catalogues that ſhall be ſent in to <hi>Edinburgh</hi> from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Paroch, and to ſet a certain price upon each Book; which general Catalogues with the price affixed to each Book, ſhall be Printed and diſtributed through every Paroch of the Kingdom, conform to which Catalogue, the Books in every Paroch ſhall be valued: or there may be laid down ſome general rules for valuing of Books at ſo much <hi>per</hi> Sheet, and ſo much for Binding.</p>
            <p>4tly. When any Miniſter ſhall die, or be removed from one Kirk to an other, then he or his Heirs or Aſſigneys, ſhall have
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:153245:7"/>right to all the Stipends of that Paroch to which he gave in his Books, ay and while he be payed of their full value conform to the Catalogue: and the Miniſters of the Presbytery ſhall ſupply that Kirk during that time, but if the Paroch cannot convenient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly want a Miniſter ſo long, then the ſucceeding Miniſter ſhall want ſuch a proportional part of the Stipend as ſhall be thought fit, which ſhall be payed yearly to the firſt Miniſter, his Heirs or aſſigneys, till the full value of his Books be payed.</p>
            <p>5thly. Where the Kirks are vacant, the Miniſters of the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterie with the Heretors of the Paroch, ſhall have power to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow all the vacant Sipends of that Kirk, upon ſuch Books as they ſhall think moſt fit and neceſſary for the Bibleotheck of that Kirk.</p>
            <p>6thly. Each Presbyterie ſhall endeavour to be a compleat Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brary within it ſelf, that is, they ſhall endeavour to have one Copy at leaſt, of every valuable Book extant in ſome one Biblio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theck or other within their bounds; wherefore it will be neceſſar that all the Miniſters in one Presbyterie, compare their Catalogues, and conſider of what Books they have more Coppies then are needful amongſt them, and what Books they think uſeful; of which they have no Coppies at all, that they may exchange the Books they have for theſe they want, conform to the value ſet on each Book by the general Catalogue.</p>
            <p>7thly. The keeper of the Bibleotheck, who may be the Reader or School-maſter of the Paroch, moſt find caution to the Miniſter and Heretors, to be faithful in keeping the Books, and in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving them from all inconveniencies; and he ſhall not lend out any Book but to an Heretor of the Paroch, or to a Miniſter of the Presbyterie, or to ſuch perſons reſiding within the Paroch as ſhall find ſufficient caution for all the Books they get out of the Library, and he ſhall take obligations from them all, that they ſhall reſtore the Books in good condition, and within ſuch a ſet time as may be ſufficient for reading the Book, but within one Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth at fartheſt; that ſo an Heretor may not defraud the reſt of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:153245:7"/>the uſe of any Book. And for preventing the imbazling the Books of thir Libraries, it is fit there be a note written upon the reverſe of the Title page, and on the laſt leaf of each Book Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by the Miniſter, declaring that the Book belongeth to the Bibleotheck of ſuch a Paroch, ſo that wherever any Book ſhall be found wanting the Title page and the laſt leaf, it may be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to be ſtollen from the Libraries, and ſo may be confiſcat to their uſe.</p>
            <p>8thly. It will be convenient that there be a Book binder ineve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Presbyterie, to bind all the Books that belong to that Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie, for which end he muſt be provided with a Houſe, and all the Inſtruments fit for his Trade, and with ſome ſmall Stipend yearly to maintain him; and then whatſoever Books he ſhall bind he ſhall be payed only for the matererials, but nothing for his work; or the keepers of the Bibleotheck or Miniſters Servants may be taught to bind Books, and may eaſiely bind all the new Books that ſhall be given in to that Library in Sheets</p>
            <p>9thly. It will be convenient that all the Bibliothicks in the Kingdom obſerve the ſame method of ranking and placeing their Books: which method may be to rank the Books according to their name and number, in the general Catalogue, which name and number muſt be written upon a piece of paper, and battered to the back of the Book, or to ſome leaf of it, that it may be eaſiely ſeen and read, by any perſon that comes into the Biblio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thick, that ſo Miniſters or Students, when they ſhall happen to remove from one Paroch or Bibliothick to another, they may not be at a loſs where to find any Book, for by this method they will pereſently know in what place every o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k ſhould ſtand.</p>
            <p>Theſe are all the particulars which I think neceſſary for the preſent for founding of Bibliothicks in every Paroch, but for the maintaining and promoting theſe 'it will be neceſſary further, that</p>
            <p>10thly. One Moneths Ceſs to be payed yearly, to be ſettled as a Fond for buying and Printing, all ſuch Books New or Old, as ſhall be judged valuable and uſefull to be diſtributed through
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:153245:8"/>the Kingdom, and every Bibliotheck in the Kingdom ſhall get a Copy of every Book that ſhall be printed: the one half of this Moneths Ceſs muſt be payed by the Heretors conform to their Valuations, the other half by the Miniſters conform to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porions of, their Stipends.</p>
            <p>11thly. This Money or Fond muſt be entruſted to ſome honeſt Perſon or Perſons, who ſhall therewith Erect a Printing-Houſe, and Paper Manufactory, and ſhall ſettle and maintain a Correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondence with all the Printing proffes abroad throughout <hi>Europe,</hi> and ſhall bring home ſome Coppies of all the Books that ſhall be Printed, as ſoon as poſſible, and ſhall Re-print all ſuch Books whether New or Old, as ſhall be judged fitting, or worthy to be diſtributed through the Kingdom, and they ſhall be oblidged to give up Accompts how the Money is beſtowed, from time to time to ſuch Miniſters and others, as ſhall be appointed to receive, and examine the ſame,</p>
            <p>12thly, A Commiſſion of the General Aſſembly muſt be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, to Reviſe all the New Books that are brought home from time to time, and to give ſome ſhort Account of them in Print, or to employ ſuch perſons as they ſhall judge moſt fit for that Work: and to Reviſe all the Old Books, and to determine what Books ſhall be Printed every Moneth, and to receive and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine the Printers Accompts.</p>
            <p>This is a Method which I think will be both eaſie and effectual for eſtabliſhing, and promoting of Bibliothecks in every Paroch throughout this Kingdom, neither do I foreſee any material Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, that can be made againſt any particular Article of it.</p>
            <p>For it ſhall be Objected againſt the ſecond Article, by ſome of the preſent Miniſters, that if they ſhall happen hereafter to be removed from their paroch to another, they will be at a great loſs for want of thoſe Books, with which they have been accuſtomed of a long time.</p>
            <p>This is eaſily anſwered, for when a Miniſter is removed from one paroch to another, he will immediatly have a right to all,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153245:8"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> at leaſe a part of the Stipends of that paroch, till he be payed for his Books, and then with that Money he may buy what Books he thinks moſt neceſſary for himſelf, and give in to the Library of that other paroch to which he ſhal be Tranſplanted, and be payed for them after his removal.</p>
            <p>It may be further Objected by the Miniſters, that when the publick is Debitor, it is ſometimes difficult to get payment; but this Objection is groundleſs here for in this caſe the publick is not Debitor, but every privat man is Debitor for his proportion of the vacant Stipends, to the Miniſter himſelf, or his Heirs and Affig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys, ay and while he be payed for all the Books he gave in to the Bibliotheck of that paroch.</p>
            <p>But that which ſhould move the Miniſters to comply willing with this Article is, that thereby they both retain the uſe of their Books, and alſo ſecure the value of them, to themſelves or their Heirs, whereas otherwiſe they might be loſt or Sold for very little</p>
            <p>It may be Objected by others againſt the tenth Article, that one Moneths Ceſs, which amounts to 72000 pounds <hi>Scots</hi> by year, will be too great a Fond for buying and printing of Books yearly</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, that if it be too great it muſt be ſo, either in reſpect of the <hi>Books</hi> it will buy and print, or in reſdect of the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> that may pay it; but it is not too great in reſpect of the <hi>Books</hi> it will buy and print, but rather too little, for the printing of an large Book as the five volumns of <hi>Pools, Criticks</hi> upon the Bible, will more than exhauſt all, and then what ſhal bring home New Books and Re-print them, and what ſhall maintain the Correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondence with all the printing places in <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither is it too great in reſpect of the <hi>Perſons</hi> that muſt pay it, for the half of it which is to be payed by the Heretors, is only the 120 part of their valued Rent, and their valued Rent is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarly but the third part of their real Rent, ſo that an Heretor of one thouſand and two hundred pounds <hi>Scots</hi> of valued Rent which is commonly 3600 pounds of real Rent, ſhall pay only ten pounds <hi>Scots</hi> yearly, for maintaining and promoting of theſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153245:9"/>Bibliothecks. And certainly it would be very unworthy of any Gentleman of ſuch a Rent, to grudge the paying of ten pound <hi>Scots</hi> yearly, when for it, he, his Children and Tennents may have the free uſe of a well furniſhed Library, and of all the new Books &amp; Gazets ſo ſoon as ever they are Printed. And I believe moſt part of Gentlemen beſtow more than this Proportion of their Rents upon Books yearly, &amp; yet are but very inſufficiently provided. Yea, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Noblemen and Gentlemen beſtow more upon News; ſo that this half Months Ceſs will be no new Burden upon them, but a more effectual and profitable way of beſtowing that Money upon Books and News, which now is Expended to little or no purpoſe.</p>
            <p>As for the other half Months Ceſs which is to be payed by the Miniſters, certainly none of them will grudge at it, ſeing any Miniſters Share of it (even although it were divided amongſt them by equal Parts) will amount only to 36 pounds <hi>Scots,</hi> which is not ſo much as the yearly Annualtent of that Sum, which now a Miniſter muſt neceſſarly be ſuppoſed to beſtow upon Books, before he can be any way tolerably furniſhed for his Studies. For ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing there be 1000 Miniſters in <hi>Scotland</hi> that ſhall have Libraries for their own uſe; then each Miniſters Share of this 36000 pounds <hi>Scots,</hi> will be only 36 pound, which is only the Annualrent of 600 pound <hi>Scots:</hi> and I believe there are few preſent Miniſters, but have beſtowed more than this Sum upon Books; ſo that the half Months Ceſs upon them, is not to be looked upon as a Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, but as a way to preſerve their Money, ſeing by this Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, the yearly Annualrent of a ſmall Sum of Money, will fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them with a compleat Library, and incomparably more Books, than both the Stock and Annualrent of a far greater Sum can do otherways.</p>
            <p>But further, there are ſeveral other Conſiderations which may make the Miniſters willing condeſcend to this Article; for either they may prevail with the king &amp; parliament to ordain this half Months Ceſs to be payed out of the Biſhops Rents, or to lay it on upon the Teinds of the Kingdom, which do juſtly belong
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153245:9"/>to the Maintainance of the Worſhip of God, or ſome honeſt hearted Patron Titular of the Teinds, may Gift or Mortifie as much as may free his Miniſter of his Proportion of it. But though none of theſe ſhould ſucceed at preſent, yet the T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cks of the Tem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s muſt run out at length, and then the Kirk will be ſufficiently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, not only to pay this half Months Ceſs, but even to pay the WHOLE, and free the Heretors of their SHARE of it.</p>
            <p>It may be objected by others, that the Fond will be too little, and the Work will be out ſmall and contemptible. But it is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, That though it may be ſmall at the beginning. yet it will not be deſpicable, for we know that <hi>Rome</hi> was not all built in one day; and it is demonſtrable, that theſe Libraries will by this Fond in a few years become very great and conſiderable, ſo that the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry meaneſt of them may compare with the moſt famous Libraries in the World; for this Fond will Print nine or ten Sheets of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per dayly, which is enough for any man to read; and this 10 Sheets dayly, will be 3000 Sheets yearly, which will be ten large Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumns of 300 Sheets to each Volumn; ſo that in 100 years, this will be 1000 large Volumns, conſiſting of three hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Sheets of Paper; which with the Books that will be given in to the Libraries from time to time, by the Miniſters and Heretors, may do much to comprehend all the valuable Books extant.</p>
            <p>But further, this Degree of Perfection in theſe Libraries, may be much ſooner attained, if the King and Parliament ſhall think fit to Augment this Ceſs upon the Heretors for ſome years, or for Printing of ſome ſelect Books; or if a more eaſie and ſpeedy way of Printing can be Invented than what is now in uſe, which I am perſwaded may be done, if men of Senſe were encouraged to apply themſelves unto it.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, it may be objected that the different Perſwaſions amongſt Miniſters may mar all this Work; But it is anſwered, That though the different Perſwaſions amongſt Miniſters, may obſtruct the free botrowing and lending of Books amongſt them, yet that needs be no hinderance to the ſettling and increaſing of the Biliothecks in every Paroch, or to the paying of their Shares for maintaining
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:153245:10"/>of the Printing Houſe, and for Printing ſuch Books as ſhall be thought moſt neceſſary.</p>
            <p>What hath been ſaid, I hope is ſufficient to convince any man, that there is no difficulty in this Work, if we be willing to ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it. Therefore I ſhall in the next place, ſay before you ſome Conſiderations taken, 1. From the Advantagiouſdeſs of the Work. 2. From the Honourableneſs of it. And 3. From the Duty that laes upon us to provide our Miniſters in all things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to their Miniſtry, which may ſerve for Arguments to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade all perſons willingly and cordially to ſet about this Work.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This Eſtabliſhing of Bibliothecks in every Paroch, will not only remedy the forementioned Inconveniencies and Difficulties of Students, but it will be ſeveral ways Advantageous to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, For 1. It will be a conſiderable Manufactory, and will Maintain many People at Work. 2. It will keep all that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney in the Kingdom, which now goes out for buying of Books and Paper. 3. It will encourage young Men to follow their Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies in their own Countrey, and thereby prevent their ſpending their Fortunes Abroad, and many other conſiderable Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies that young Men are expoſed unto in ſtrange Countreys. 4. It will allure and provoke Gentlemen to beſtow their ſpare Hours in reading of new Books, which may prove a good Means to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain them from Gaming and Drinking, by preventing that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie and weariſome Idleneſs of Mind, which is the Parent of theſe, and many other Enormities. 5. It will in a ſhort time, carry away the whole Trade of Printing from all the reſt of <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But 2. As this Eſtabliſhing of Bibliothecks in every Paroch will be Advantageous, ſo it will be very Honourable to this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey. For 1. We ſhall not only be the firſt and the only Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for a while, that ſhal have this regular and uſeful plenty of Books. But 2 Hereby all ſorts of Learning will mightily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and flouriſh amongſt us, and though we be not a great or a rich People, yet we may be a wiſe and a learned People. Yea further, theſe Libraries in two or three hundred years will be ſo full and compleat, that the moſt Famous and Magnificent Libra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:153245:10"/>in the World, ſhal not out do the meaneſt Library in any Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roch of this Kingdom, for numbers of valuable and uſeful Books, as hath been already demonſtrat.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If it be our Duty to provide our Miniſters with all things neceſſary for them as a competent Stipend, Manſe and Gleib, that they being free from worldly Cares, may have time to ſtudy and Inſtruct their People. Then certainly it muſt much more be our Duty, to provide them with competent Libraries of the moſt uſeful Books, ſeing without theſe they cannot ſtudy, nor be fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſufficiently for Inſtructing their People in the Truths of their Religion.</p>
            <p>4thly. Seing God hath made all men by nature deſirous of Knowledge, undoubtedly the ſatisfying of this deſire, muſt be a conſiderable part of our natural felicity; for the only delight of our Souls, which are our better part, in which the Body doth not partake, is the delight She taketh in Knowledge and Contemplation. And ſeing God hath ſo ordered it, that the moſt part of our Knowledge ſhould be communicat to us from our Fore-fathers, and Contemporaries, eſpecially by their Books and Writings. It doth neceſſarly follow, that the eſtabliſhing and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting of Libraries in every Paroch, whereby the uſe of all ſorts of Books may be rendered moſt free and univerſal, and may be perfectly ſecured to all our poſterity, will be a very effectual means of increaſing Knowledge and Learning amongſt us, and of helping us, and our poſterity to ſearch out all the Works of our God, that we may admire and adore his Infinit Wiſdom and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, in making them ſuch, and in ſo wouderfully diſpoſing of them for his own purpoſes and Glory, which ſeems to be one principal end, for which our Bleſſed Maker hath made us ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ual Creatures.</p>
            <p>Theſe things being duely conſidered, I hope what hath been ſaid will be ſufficient, to perſwade all lovers, and encouragers of Learning, that this founding and promoting of Bibliothecks in every Paroch throughout this Kingdom, is both neceſſary and eaſie, advantagious and honourable, our Intereſt and our Duty,</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
